data structures and algorithms, we are going to learn today some basic terminology regarding
data structures and the notations that we would be following in the rest of this course.
We will begin with just some very simple definitions, an algorithm which is an outline
of the steps that a program has to take or any computational procedure has to take.
A program on the other hand is an implementation of an algorithm, it could be in any programming
language. A data structure is the way we need to organize the data so that it can be used
effectively by the program. So you all are familiar with certain data structures, an
array or a list for instance. So this course is about you will be seeing a lot more data
structures in this course and you will see how to use them in various algorithms. So we
will take a particular problem try to solve that problem and in the process develop data
structures the best way of organizing the data associated with that problem.
So what is an algorithmic problem? An algorithmic problem is essentially that you have a certain
specification of an input as is given here and I use specify what the output should
be like and the specification of an input could be well here is one specification assorted
non-decreasing sequence of natural numbers of non-zero finite plane that is an input that
is a completely specified input. I have given two examples here of inputs which meet the
specification. I have not given any output specification yet here. Now what is an
instance? These are two instances of the input. This is the specification for the input and
you can have any possible instance. You can take any sequence of sorted non-decreasing numbers
and that would form an input instance. So there are infinitely many input instances
possible here. So an algorithm is essentially describing the actions that one should take
on the input instance to get an output as is desired as is specified and again just as there
can be infinitely many input instances there can be infinitely many algorithms for solving
a certain problem. Each one of you could do it in a slightly different way. So that
brings us to the notion of a good algorithm. If there are so many different algorithms
for solving a certain problem what is a good algorithm?
A good algorithm for us is an efficient algorithm. Anything that is efficient is good and what
is efficient? Efficient is something which has small running time and takes less memory.
These will be the two measures of efficiency that we will be working with. There could
be other measures of efficiency but these are the only two we would be considering in
this course and most of our time we would be spending with running time really. Space
of course will also be analyzing the space but most of the time would be spent in worrying
about the running time of our algorithm and we would be interested in the efficiency of
algorithms as a function of the input size. So clearly you can imagine that if I have
a small input and my algorithm running on that input will take or my program running
on that input will take less amount of time. If the input becomes 10 times larger then
the time taken by the program would also grow. May be it becomes 10 times, may be it becomes
20 times, may be it becomes 100 times. I do not know. So it is this behavior of the increase
in the running time with the increase in the size of the input that we would also
be of interest to us. We will come to all of these in a short while as we go through
these slides. Now how does one measure running time? I said efficiency, running
time, very important first. So how does one measure the running time of an algorithm? So
one way would be to what I have put down here as an experimental study. You have a certain
algorithm, you implement that algorithm which means you write a program in a certain programming
language. You run the program with varying data sets. So some smaller, some larger
data sets, some would be of some kind, some would be of a different kind. So varying
composition and then you clock the time that the program takes and clock does not mean that
you sit down with a stopwatch, you would perhaps just use a system utility like let us say system
current time may less to clock the time that the program takes and then from that you
try and figure out how good your algorithm is. So that is what one would call an experimental
study of the algorithm. Now this has certain limitations. So I have put them down, first
you have to implement the algorithm. To be able to determine how good your algorithm is
you have to implement it. Now that is already a huge overhead. Considerable amount of time
has to be spent in doing this. Then your experiments can be done only on a limited
set of inputs. After all I said the number of instances is infinitely large. You cannot
be running, you can only run your experiment on a small set of instances and that might
not really be indicative of the time that your algorithm is taking for other inputs which
you have not considered in your experiment. Further if you have two algorithms and you
have to decide which is better, you have to use exactly the same platforms to do
the comparison. By platform I mean both the hardware and the software environments because
as you can imagine different machines would make a difference not just different machines.
In fact even the users who are working on that system at that particular point would make
a difference on the running time of your algorithm. So it becomes very messy if you have to do
it this way. So what we are going to do as part of this course and in fact in this
very first lecture is to develop a general methodology which will help us analyze the
running time of algorithms. We are going to do it as follows. We are going to first
develop a high level description of an algorithm, a way of describing an algorithm and we are
going to use this description to figure out the running time and not implement it or any
such thing. Our methodology would help us take into account all possible input instances
and it will allow us to evaluate the efficiency of the algorithm in a way that is independent
of the environment, independent of the platform that we are using. I said we will give a high
level description of the algorithm. This very first point here we will give a high level.
What is this? This brings me to what we will call pseudocode and this is how we are
going to be specifying all our algorithms for the purposes of this course.
Here is an example of a pseudocode and you might have seen this in your earlier
courses also. What is this algorithm doing? This algorithm takes an array A which stores
an integer in it and it is trying to find the maximum element in this array. What I have
written here is not a program because I think the syntax is all wrong but it is a pseudocode.
It is a mixture of natural language and some high level programming constructs. I am going
to come to all of that but I am going to be using like a for, do, loop. I am going to use
an if then else statement. I am going to use a while loop. All of that I will use but
I will not bother about there should be a semicolon here or there should be a colon
here. I am not going to bother about those things that are required by a compiler but
for our understanding this is completely clear what this program is doing. What is this doing?
It is keeping track of the maximum variable in a variable called current max which is initialized
to the first element of the array and then it is going to run through the remaining elements
of the array, compare them with the current maximum element that we have seen. If the
current maximum element that we have is less than the current element under consideration
then it would update current max. AI becomes the new max and then when this loop terminates
we would just return current max. So it is a very simple algorithm but just with this
pseudocode you are able to understand what it is doing. This will not run on any computer
it is pseudocode but it conveys the ideas, it conveys the concepts. Any questions to
this point? So that is what I was saying it is more structured, pseudocode is more structured
than usual prose but it is less formal than a programming language. What will our pseudocode
look like? We will use standard numeric and Boolean expressions in it. Instead of the
assignment operator which is equal to n java I will use this left arrow and instead
of the equality operator, equality relationship in java which is 2 equals the same in C I will
use just the single equal. I will declare methods in this manner. So algorithm name, what are
the parameters it takes? I will use all kinds of programming constructs. I will use if then
else statements while do repeat until for do to index arrays I will say a i, a i, j so on
and on. It should be clear what this is doing and I will use return when the procedure terminates
and return value will tell me what is the value returned by the particular procedure or
a function and when I have to make a call to a method I will specify that with method
name of the method, the argument and what is the object that it is reserving. Any questions
to this point? This is specifying the type of the value returned by the particular method.
You will see more of this when we come across more pseudocode. So how do we analyze algorithms?
So we identify what are primitive operations in our pseudocode. So what is a primitive operation?
It is a low level operation. Examples, data movement. I do an assignment from one to another.
I do a control statement which is a branch if then else, a subroutine call, a return
or I do arithmetic operations or logical operations. These are all we will call them primitive
operations and in my pseudocode I just inspect the pseudocode and count the number of primitive
operations that are executed by the algorithm. So we need to take an example now. I will take
an example of sorting. You all know what sorting is. The input is some sequence of
numbers. Output is a permutation of the sequence which is in non-decreasing order. So if
this were my input this should be my output. What are the requirements of the output?
We said it should be in non-decreasing order and it should be a permutation of the input.
Any set of numbers which are in non-decreasing order does not make an output. Your algorithm
should sort the numbers that were given to it not just produce a sequence of numbers
in increasing order. Clearly the running time will depend upon how many elements are
there and quite often it depends upon how sorted these numbers were.
If they were already almost sorted then perhaps your algorithm is not going to take a long time.
Of course it also depends upon what particular algorithm you are using. So the running time
would depend upon all of these factors. The first sorting technique we are going
to use is one that you have used very often. Let us say when you are playing a game of
cards. So what is the strategy you follow when you are picking up set of cards that have
been dealt out to you? You like to keep them in a sorted order in your hand. So you start
with your empty hand, you pick up the first card then you take the next card and you
insert it at the appropriate place. Suppose you have some 5 cards in your hand already
let us say 2, 7, 9, Jack and Queen then I get an 8 so I am going to put it between 7 and
9. That is the right place it has to be in. So I am inserting it at the appropriate place
and that is why this technique is called insertion sorting and I keep doing this till
I have picked up all the cards and inserted them appropriately in the hand that I have.
So what is the idea? This is the pseudo code for insertion sort and we will just run through
this so that you all understand. I give you as input an array of integers let us say A contains
the input. The output is a permutation of the original numbers such that it is sorted.
So my output is also going to be in the same array. This is the input output specification.
I am going to have two variables or two indices i and j. The array is going to be sorted from
A1 through Ai at any point in time. A1 through Aj minus 1 is going to be sorted. The jth location
is the element which I have to insert appropriately at the right place. So clearly j then has
to vary from 2 to n. So j has to vary from 2 to n. So I am going to look at the jth element.
I put that in key and now this is what I have to do. I have to insert Aj or I have to insert
the key into the sorted sequence which is A1 through Aj minus 1. A1 through Aj minus 1 is
the sorted sequence and I am going to use the index i to help me do this. What is index
i going to do? Index i is going to run down from j minus 1 down to 1. We are going to decrease
index i which is what we are doing here in this while do loop. It starts with the value
j minus 1 and what am I going to do? Let us see what am I going to do here? I have to insert
7. I am going to move this 9 to this location. Why? Because 9 is more than 7. So 9 is more
than 7 and I move it here. Then I compare 7 with 8. 7, 8 is still more than 7. So
7 with 6. 6 is smaller than 7. So now I have found the right place for 7 and I would put
7 in here. That is exactly what is happening in here. I run through this loop till I find
an element which is less than key. Key is the element I am trying to insert. So this
loop will continue while the element I am considering is more than key. This loop
will terminate when I see an element which is less than key or the loop will terminate
when I reach i equals 0. In which case that means that I have moved everything to the right
and I should insert the element in the very first place. What am I doing here? I am just
shifting the element one step to the right. Note that I have to insert this at the
right place. I shift 9, right one step. Now this location becomes empty. So to say
then I shift 8 one step. So this location now becomes empty and now I can come and put 7 in
here which is what I do eventually. So i plus 1 would be the index where this location which
would be the empty location eventually and I put in key there. So it is a very you can
all implement it. Maybe you would have implemented it in a slightly different way that would
give you a different program. But the algorithm is essentially the same. You are going to
find the right place for the element and insert it there. And now let us try and analyze this
algorithm. So I put down the algorithm here on the left. There is a small mistake here.
This should be a left arrow. Please make a correction of that. What we are going to
do is let us count. So these are all my primitive operations. This is a primitive operation.
This is a primitive operation. Here I have two primitive operations really. Why? Because
I am comparing i with 0 and I am comparing a i with key and actually I am also taking
an and. So there are three primitive operations. So there are certain number of primitive operations
here. This is also primitive. So all of these are primitive operations. And what I am
doing here? So each of these operations take a certain amount of time depending upon the
computer system you have. So c1, c2, c3, c4, c5, c5, c6 just reflect or just represent
the amount of time that these operations take. In whatever units I do not care. And here
I am counting the number of times each of these operations is executed is done in this
entire program. Now why is this operation done n times? It says n times. So I start by assigning
j equals 2 then assign 3, 4, 5, 6, 7. I go all the way up to n and then when I increment it
may be once and I check that oh no it is now more. So I have counted it as n times.
So there might be small errors in n and n plus 1. That is not very important. So this
is roughly n times that we have to do this operation. How about this operation? I am going
to do it exactly n minus 1 times. Once for 2, once for 3, once for 4 up to n. So that is
why I have that this operation is being done n minus 1 times. Let us forget this is just
a common statement. Again this operation will be done exactly n minus 1 times. Now
we have to look at how many times this particular how many times do I come to this
statement. T sub j reflects the accounts the number of times I have to shift an element to
the right when I am inserting the jth card into my hand. So in the previous example when
I am inserting 7 I had to shift 2 elements 8 and 9. So T sub j is going to be counting
that quantity and that is the number of times I am going to reach this part of my while loop.
I am going to be checking this condition. So first I come to this condition then maybe
I come again to this condition. I come again over and over again to this condition. So
the jth iteration of this for loop I am going to reach this condition T sub j times. So the
total number of times I am seeing this condition is the sum of T sub j as j goes from 2 to n.
So every time I see this condition I also come here. I am going to be seeing this condition.
I am going to come to this statement one more time than I come here because the last
time I see this statement I would exit out of here. So that is why this is T j minus
1 and similarly for that same reason this is T j minus 1, j going from 2 to n. This statement
here is not part of this while loop. This is an assignment operation. Please correct this.
This is not part of the while loop and so this statement is part of the for loop and
it is done exactly n minus 1 times as other statements.
And so the total time that this procedure takes if you knew what these constants were
can be computed in this manner. Of course you do not know what T sub j is. T sub j is a quantity
which depends upon your instance. Not problem. There is a difference here. Problem is one
of sorting. The instance is the set of numbers, the sequence of numbers that is given to
you. So T sub j depends upon the instance and let us see what difference T sub j makes.
So if the input was already sorted, T sub j is always 1. I just have to compare the element
with the last element and I will immediately see that it is larger than the last element
and so I would not have to do anything at all. So T sub j is always a 1 if the input
is already in increasing order. What happens when the input is in decreasing order? If the
input is in decreasing order then the number that I am trying to insert is going to be
smaller than all the numbers that I already have because the input is in decreasing order.
The number I am trying to insert is smaller than the numbers that I already have sorted
in my array. So what am I going to do? I am going to compare it with the first
element, the second element, the third element, the fourth element all the way up to the very
first element. So when I am trying to insert the jth element I am actually going to end
up comparing it with all the other j elements in the array and so in that case T sub j will
be equal to j and when T sub j equals j, note what this quantity becomes. It is summation
j, j going from 2 to n. You all know it is of the kind n squared and in that
case the running time of this algorithm would be some constant times n squared plus some
other constant times n minus some other constant. The behavior of this running time is more of
more like n squared. We come to this point later when we are talking of a symptotic
analysis but this is what I mean by f of n squared. It will behave more like n squared.
Here on the other hand in the best case when Tj was 1, this sum here is just n or
n minus 1 and in that case the total time is n times some constant plus n minus 1 times some
constant minus some constant which is roughly n times some constant. So it is what we call
the linear time algorithm. I come to these things again. On an average what would you
expect? In the best case it is something like that you have to compare only against
one element. In the worst case you have to compare about j elements. In the average
case you would expect that you would compare against half of those elements. In the average
case if you were to take it as you are comparing against j by 2, even then this quantity summation
of j by 2, j going from 2 to n, what will this be? This will be roughly n squared by
4 now. So its behavior is again like n squared and we come to these points in a minute.
So this is what I mean by best, worst and average case. So I take the size of the input suppose
I am interested in sorting n numbers and I look at all possible instances of these n numbers
infinitely many. So again it is not clear how exactly one would do that. So what is
worst case defined as? Worst case is defined as the maximum possible time that your algorithm
would take for any instance of that size. So these are all instances of the same size.
The best case would be the smallest time that your algorithm would take and the average would
be the average of all of these infinitely many bars. So that was for inputs of one size
n. That would give us the values of we can then therefore compute worst case, best case
and average case. Now if I were to consider inputs of all sizes I can then create a plot
of this kind. For each input size I can figure out, suppose I could figure out what the
worst case, best case and average case were then I would get such monotonically increasing
plots. Why is that? It is clear that as the size of the input increases the time taken with
your algorithm will increase. It is not going to happen that your input size becomes larger
and it takes lesser time. So which of these is of interest to us or which of this is
easiest to work with? Worst case is the one that we will use most often and for
why is that? First it provides an upper bound. It tells you how long your algorithm is going
to take in the worst case. Many algorithms it occurs fairly often. Quite often it is
the case that your worst case that for many instances the time taken by the algorithm
is close to the worst case. So that average case essentially becomes as bad as the worst
case. In fact for the previous example that we saw, average case was like n squared and
worst case was also like n squared. Of course there were a difference in the constant but
it was roughly the same. Now average case might be a very difficult quantity to compute
because as I said average case if you have to compute you have to look at all possible
instances and then take some kind of an average. Or you have to say my input instances
are drawn from a certain distribution and so the expected time my algorithm will take
if an input instance is drawn from this distribution is going to be similar. So it is typically
a much harder quantity to work with and compute. So worst case is the measure of interest
is what we will be working with.
So asymptotic analysis is the kind of a thing that we have been doing so far when
I said n squared and n and the goal of this is really to analyze the running time while
getting rid of superficial details. We would like to say that an algorithm which has a running
time of some constant times n squared is the same as an algorithm which has a running
time of some other constant times n squared. Why? Because this constant is typically
something which would be dependent upon the hardware that you are using. In the example
that I showed you the C1, C2, C3 all of those times would depend upon the computer system
that you are using. The hardware, the compiler, many many factors and so we would not like
to distinguish or we are not interested or we are not bothered about distinguishing
between such algorithms. Both of these algorithms one which has a running time of 3 n squared
perhaps or another with the running time of n squared have a quadratic behavior as in when
the input size doubles both of the algorithm their running time increases 4 fold and that
is the thing that is of interest to us.
We are interested in capturing how the running time of the algorithm increases with the size
of the input in the limit. This is the crucial point here and that is what asymptotic
analysis is all about. That is what the asymptotic here is. In the limit how does the running time
of this algorithm increase with increase in input size.
That brings us to something that some of you might have seen before the Bego notation.
So if I have functions f of n and g of n, f of n and g of n, n here is typically representing
the input size. f of n is measuring the time that your algorithm is taking. So f of n and
g of n are both non-negative functions not just non-negative they are also non-decreasing
because as input sizes increases the value of the running time, the time taken by your
algorithm would also increase.
So these are both non-decreasing functions of n and we say that f of n is Big O of g of n.
If there exists constant c and n0 such that f of n is less than c times g of n for n larger
than n0. So what does all of this mean? So I have drawn two functions here. The function
in red is f of n and g of n is some other function. This function in green is some constant
n times g of n. Now as you can see beyond this point n0, c times g of n is always larger than
f of n. So suppose this is the way it continues even beyond this point. Then we would say that
f of n is Big O of g of n or f of n is order g of n. So a few examples would clarify this
and we come to that.
My function f of n here is 2n plus 6 and g of n is n. It is the case, if you look at these
two functions 2n plus 6 is always larger than n. So which is why this function 2n plus 6
is always above n. Now you might be wondering why 2n plus 6 is a non-linear function
here. That is because the scale here is an exponential scale. So it is 2 to the 0 to the
1 to the 2 and so on and similarly on this axis. So this is n and this blue line here
is 2n and this is 4n. Now as you can see beyond this point f of n is less than 4 times n.
So what are our constant c and n0? The constant c is 4 and n0 would be this point of crossing
beyond which 4n becomes larger than 2n plus 6. What is this point of crossing? At what
point does 4n become larger than 2n plus 6? 3. So your n0 becomes 3 and then we say
that f of n which is 2n plus 6 is big O of g of n. Not big O of 4n but big O of n. So f of
n here is big O of n. So 2n plus 6 is big O of n. Another example, the function in red
is g of n which is n and any constant time g of n, so it is the same scale as in the
previous line. Any constant time g of n will just be the same straight line displaced by
suitable amount. So this will be 4, this will be 4 times n, this will be whatever depends
upon what the intercept here is. So it will just be like this but your n squared would
be a line like this. So there is no constant c such that n square is less than c of n.
Can you find out a constant c such that n square is less than c of n for n more than n0? No. Any
constant that you choose I can pick a larger n. I can pick an n such that this is violated
and so it is not the case that n square is big O of n. So how does one figure out these
things? So there is a very simple rule. Suppose this is my function 50n log n. I just drop
all constants and lower order terms. So forget the constant 50 here and I get n log n. So this
is big O of n log n. This function 50n log n is big O of n log n. 7n minus 3 is I drop
the constant and lower order terms I get 7n minus 3 is big O of n. I have some complicated
function like 8n square log n plus 5n square plus n. I just drop all lower order terms.
This is the fastest growing term because this has n square as well as log n in it. So I just
drop the n square and n term and from here I drop my constant and I get n square log n.
So this function is big O of n square log n. There is a constant c such that this quantity
this large sum here is less than c times n square log n for n larger than some n0.
In the limit this quantity will be less than some constant times this quantity and you can
figure out what the value of c should be and what the value of n0 should be for that to
happen.
This is a common error. So this function 50n log n is also big O of n to the 5. Why?
Because this quantity in fact is less than or equal to 50 times n to the 5 always for all
n and that is just a constant. So this is big O of n to the 5. But when we use the big
O notation we try and provide as strong a bound as possible. So instead of saying while
this statement is true we will rather call this as big O of n log n. You will see more
of this in subsequent slides. So how are we going to use the big O notation? So we are going
to express the number of primitive operations that are executed during a run of the program
as a function of the input set. We are going to use the big O notation for that. Now if
I have an algorithm for which the number of primitive operations is big O of n and
some other algorithm for which the number of primitive operations is big O of n square
then clearly the first algorithm is better than the second. Why? Because as the input
size grows, if the input size doubles then the running time of this algorithm is only
going to double while the running time of this algorithm will increase fourfold. Similarly
our algorithm which has a running time of big O of log n is better than one which has
a running time of big O of n. And we have a hierarchy of functions of this kind log
n n n square and an algorithm with the running time of big O of log n is better than one with
the big O of n with better than one with the big O of running time of big O of n square
running time of big O of n cube which is better than an algorithm with the running time of
big O of 2 to the n. So there is a word of caution here. You might have an algorithm
whose running time is a million times n because you are doing a whole lot of maybe
some other operations. I cannot see how you would create such an algorithm but you might
have an algorithm of this running time. So this is big O of n because this is less than or
equal to some constant times n and you might have some other algorithm with the running
time of 2 n square. So from what I have said before you would say that this algorithm
is better than this. The one with the linear running time of big O of n running time is
better than this. It is true but in the limit and the limit here is achieved very late when
n is really really large. For small instances this 2 n square might actually take less time
than your 1 million times n. So you have to be careful about the constants also.
So we will do some examples of asymptotic analysis. So I have a pseudocode written here and what
I am doing here is I have an array of numbers, n numbers sitting in an array called x and
I have to output an array a in which each element in which the element ai is the average of the
numbers x0 through xi. This is what I have to do. So what is one way of doing it? So I
basically have a for loop in which I compute each element of the array a. So to compute
a10 what should I do? I just have to sum up x0 through x10 which I am doing here. So what
is this doing? When I am computing a10 i is taking the value 10 and I am running the
index j from 0 to 10. I am summing up the value of x0 plus x1 up to x10 in this accumulator
a and then I am eventually dividing the value of this accumulator with 11 because it is x0
through x10 and that gives me the number that I should have in a10 and I am going to repeat
this for 11, 12, 13, 14 all the elements essentially. Is this a good algorithm? It is not a good
algorithm. This is one step. How many times is this step executed? It is executed i times
and what are the values that i takes? Initially i takes a value 0 to 1, 2, 3 all the way up
to n minus 1 and this entire thing is done n times. So what does that give you? That
gives you total running time of roughly n square. This one step is getting executed n square
times and this is the dominant thing. Of course how many times is this step getting executed?
This step is getting executed n times and so is this step which is getting executed n times
but this step is getting executed roughly n square times, some constant times n square
times and so running time of your algorithm is bigger of n square. It is a very simple
problem but you can have a better solution here and perhaps all of you can see what
the better solution should be. What is the better solution? We will have a variable s in
which we would keep accumulating the x i's. Initially s is just 0 and then when I am computing
because I used that at the last step. That is the problem that is happening here. See every
time we are computing x, so first we are computing x0 plus x1, then we are computing x0 plus x1
plus x2, then we are computing x0 plus x1 plus x2 plus x3. We are kind of repeating
computations over and over again. Why should we do that? We will have just the single
variable which will keep track of the prefixes, the sum of the prefixes so far. So s at
this point when I am in the ith run of this loop, s at that point already has the sum x0
through x i minus 1 and then I sum x i in it and to compute the ith element I just need
to divide this sum by i plus 1. I keep this accumulator round with me. Now when I finish
the ith run, ith iteration of this loop I have in s x0 through x i, the sum x0
through x i. I can reuse it for the next step. So how much time does this take now? In each
run of this loop I am just doing two steps, two primitive operations. So that makes it
order n time because this loop is executed n times.
So I have been using this freely, linear and quadratic but here is a slide which just
tells you the other terms that I might be using. So linear if an algorithm has a running
time, I say an asymptotic running time of order n, then we call it a linear algorithm. If it
has an asymptotic running time which is n squared, we call it quadratic. Logarithmic
if it is log n, polynomial if it has n to the k for some constant k, k is a constant
here. And an algorithm is called exponential if it has a running time of a to the n
where a is some number more than 1. So till now I have only introduced to you the big o
notation. We also have the big omega notation and the big theta notation. The big omega
notation provides a lower bound. A function f of n is omega of g of n. So this is f of
n, this is constant times g of n. If constant times g of n is always less than f of n,
earlier this was more than f of n, less than f of n in the limit. So beyond a certain n0
as this picture illustrates. So f of n is more than c times g of n beyond this point n0 and
that case we will say that f of n is omega of g of n. The theta notation f of n is theta
of g of n if there exist constant c1 and c2 such that f of n is sandwiched between
c1 times g of n and c2 times g of n. That is beyond a certain point f of n lies between
one constant times g of n and another constant times g of n. So then we say that f of n is
theta of g of n. That is f of n grows like g of n in the limit. Another way of thinking
of it is f of n is theta of g of n if f of n is big o of g of n and it is also
omega of g of n. This part tells you that f of n is big o of g of n and this part tells
you that f of n is omega of g of n and so we have that f of n is theta of g of n.
There are two more related asymptotic notations. One is called the little o notation and the
other is called the little omega notation. They are the non tight analogues of big
o and sorry they are the non tight analogues of big o and big omega and it is best to understand
this through the analogy with real numbers. So when I say that f of n is big o of g of
n, I am really saying that the function f is in some sense less than or equal to g.
That is in fact what we used in the definition. f of n is less than c times g of n. So f
the analogy with real numbers is when a number is less than or equal to another number. Omega
is for greater than or equal to theta is equal to of course these are functions while these
are real numbers. So if these are real numbers you can talk of equality but you cannot talk
of equality of functions unless they are exactly equal. So this is the corresponding notion
for that. Little o now corresponds to strictly less and little omega corresponds to strictly
more. So we are not going to be using these. In fact we will be spending most of our time
with just big o. So that is the part you should be very clear with.
What do we specifically mean that it is strictly?
For that I will just maybe look at the slide. So the formal definition for little
o is that for every constant c there should exist some n0 such that f of n is less than
c times g of n for n more than n0. How is it different from big o? There it said there
exists a c and an n0 such that this is true. Here we want to say for every c there should
exist an n0 for which this is true. So this is just one slide that I put up to
show what the difference between these functions is like. So suppose I have algorithms whose running
times are like 400 n, 20 n, log n, 2 n square, n to the 4, n to the n and here I list out
what is the largest problem size you can solve in one second, one minute and one hour.
So the largest problem size you can solve is roughly 2500. Say this is using some
fail, some constant. So it is let us say 2500. If you had this as your running time let us
say this is what the problem size would be like. Why do you see that this is larger than
this? Although this is a worse running time than this in big o because of the constants.
So you see the difference happening here. If it is 2 n square then it is already only
a problem of size 7 or 7 that you can solve. If it is 2 to the n you can only solve the
problem of size 19 and see how the behavior is as the time increases. An hour is 3600 seconds
and so you see a huge increase in the size of the problem you can solve if it were a
linear time algorithm. Still a large increase when it is an n log n algorithm not so large
an increase when it is an n square algorithm and almost no increase when it is a 2 to the
n algorithm. If you have an algorithm which is running time of something like 2 to the n
you cannot solve a problem of more than size 100. Cannot solve means it will take millions
of years for you to do that. So that is the behavior that bothers us that is the behavior
we are interested in in this course. That is why asymptotic analysis is what we will
be considering most often. So any questions till this point? With that we are going to stop
this lecture. Today we have looked at asymptotic analysis and some initial notation and terminology
that we will be following with this course.